<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Corpus Design on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</title><link>/tags/corpus-design/</link><description>Recent content in Corpus Design on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/corpus-design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SindBERT</title><link>/project/sindbert/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/sindbert/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="sindbert--the-turkish-model-that-started-a-new-chapter">SindBert – The Turkish Model That Started a New Chapter&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>SindBert started as an exploratory attempt to bring high-quality RoBERTa-style language modeling to Turkish. The idea originally emerged during the broader multilingual phase that followed GottBERT, GeistBERT, ChristBERT, HalleluBERT and PortBERT. After finishing PortBERT, the timing finally felt right to extend this line of research to another underrepresented language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the pipeline already stable from previous projects, we created the first large-scale RoBERTa-style Turkish model. This makes SindBert a significant technical milestone within the landscape of Turkish transformer models, and an important step toward raising Turkish NLP to the architectural standards used in higher-resource languages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study behind SindBert was conducted with considerable care. We systematically reviewed existing Turkish models and evaluated them across an extensive set of downstream benchmarks. The evaluation was carried out in two stages: first on a private workstation with two RTX 3090 GPUs in SLI, and later on the LRZ BayernKI H100 cluster, which enabled the training and assessment of the large SindBert variants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A key insight from the study was that the performance of Turkish models is not driven simply by corpus size. Extremely large corpora did not consistently translate into stronger results. Instead, the best performance came from models trained on corpora with moderate size but high internal variance and quality. This finding reinforces the idea that thoughtful corpus design often matters more than sheer quantity for languages with complex morphology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although SindBERT does not yet have a formal publication attached to it, the project marks the beginning of a new chapter in my international research. It follows directly after PortBERT and represents the point where the broader model family began to expand into new linguistic territory. The work was completed in Freiburg at my new research institution, where the evaluations and analyses were finalized. SindBERT may evolve further or be revisited in a second iteration, but even in its current form it stands as the first large Turkish RoBERTa-style model and an important step toward stronger transformer development for the Turkish language. A preprint of the work is available, and the paper has been submitted to SIGTURK@EACL 2026.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links--resources">Links &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Preprint (2025):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21364">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21364&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>🤗 &lt;strong>HuggingFace Model Hub:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/SindBERT">https://huggingface.co/SindBERT&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>ChristBERT</title><link>/project/christbert/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/christbert/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="building-a-medical-german-language-model-against-the-odds">Building a Medical German Language Model Against the Odds&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>ChristBERT was developed as part of my Master’s thesis and focuses on domain-specific German clinical language modeling. The project investigated two complementary strategies: continued pre-training on top of GottBERT/GeistBERT, and training from scratch using both a general-purpose RoBERTa tokenizer and a specialized medical vocabulary. This enabled a systematic comparison between general, domain-adapted, and fully specialized pre-training pipelines for German medical NLP.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the early conceptual phase, the supervision structure of the thesis changed, and the project was reassigned to a new advisor, who later became the supervisor of my doctoral work. ChristBERT was trained using a combination of compute resources: through an existing project partnership, parts of the full pre-training were executed on the Augsburg compute cluster, while downstream evaluations, and parts of the translation workflows ran on privately built GPU hardware in my basement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ChristBERT showed that continued pre-training on German clinical text offers measurable improvements over general-purpose RoBERTa models, while training from scratch with a medical-specific tokenizer provides additional insights into domain vocabulary specialization and its trade-offs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The work has been released as a preprint and is currently under review at BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links--resources">Links &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Preprint (2025):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-7332811/v1">https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-7332811/v1&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>🤗 &lt;strong>HuggingFace Model Hub:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/ChristBERT">https://huggingface.co/ChristBERT&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>GeistBERT</title><link>/project/geistbert/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/geistbert/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-story-of-resilience-constraint-and-scientific-maturity">A Story of Resilience, Constraint, and Scientific Maturity&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>GeistBERT was created during one of the most turbulent and defining phases of my doctoral work. AFollowing a supervisor transition at TUM, access to the compute environment I previously used was no longer available, so I migrated the entire evaluation workflow to my own workstation. What could have halted the project entirely instead became a turning point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With no cluster access, I migrated the full evaluation pipeline into my basement and ran it on a self-built workstation with two RTX 3090 GPUs in SLI. Every downstream task was completed entirely on private hardware. Constraints turned into autonomy, and the work slowly took shape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At that time, the plan was more ambitious:&lt;br>
we intended to train Longformer- and Nyströmformer-based variants of GottBERT to compare sparse-attention architectures in continued pre-training on a GPU setup. However, an unnoticed mistake in the pre-training made these large-scale models useless. Instead of releasing partially flawed or inconclusive models, we made the conscious decision to retract the extended architectures and focus the paper on a clean, well-defined contribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The final version of GeistBERT therefore centered on what was both scientifically solid and practically valuable:&lt;br>
a robust RoBERTa-base model with continued pre-training, using Whole Word Masking and a large, diverse corpus, carefully evaluated across standard German NLP benchmarks.&lt;br>
Despite being a base model, GeistBERT achieved state-of-the-art performance in multiple tasks and approached, and in some benchmarks even surpassed, the performance of existing large models.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During this phase, GeistBERT also revealed an interesting methodological insight:&lt;br>
unlike earlier TPU-based experiments, the GPU training workflow allowed for a substantially higher peak learning rate without instability. This raised new research questions about whether the stability originated from implementation differences in the GPU stack, or whether it was a characteristic of continued pre-training itself. These observations gave the project an additional scientific dimension beyond the model alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The manuscript was completed far from Germany, during a research stay on the Azores, and released as a pre-print. Later, GeistBERT found its academic platform at &lt;a href="https://globalnlp2025.github.io">GlobalNLP2025@RANLP 2025&lt;/a> in Varna, Bulgaria.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links--resources">Links &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Preprint (2025):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11903">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11903&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>🤗 &lt;strong>HuggingFace Model Hub:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/GeistBERT">https://huggingface.co/GeistBERT&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>