<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C++ on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</title><link>/tags/c++/</link><description>Recent content in C++ on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/c++/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Volume Renderer for use with MATLAB</title><link>/project/volume-renderer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/volume-renderer/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="from-a-student-project-to-a-polished-tool-gpu-volume-rendering-for-matlab">From a student project to a polished tool: GPU volume rendering for MATLAB&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Volume Renderer for use with MATLAB started as my master project at the University of Freiburg in 2012, supervised by Benjamin Ummenhofer and apl. Prof. Dr. Olaf Ronneberger. At the time, MATLAB offered only limited support for interactive, high quality volume rendering of 3D data on the GPU, especially for larger medical volumes and multi volume scenes. The project filled this gap by adding a GPU enabled volume render command to MATLAB that could be used directly from scripts and applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The core renderer is written in CUDA C and C++, while the user interface is provided through a set of MATLAB classes. This design separates performance critical code from user facing logic and allowed us to integrate advanced rendering concepts into a familiar MATLAB workflow. Users can call the renderer like any other MATLAB function, yet the heavy lifting happens on the GPU.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A central feature of the system is its custom memory management. GPU memory is limited, but many use cases require rendering multiple large volumes in a single scene. To address this, the renderer splits the scene into separate rendering passes that fit into GPU memory, then combines the resulting images inside MATLAB into a single final frame. On top of that, volumes are only transferred to the GPU when the underlying data changes, which keeps repeated renders fast by reusing GPU memory across calls.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The renderer also implements a generic illumination model that can be extended with different phase functions. The provided implementation uses the Henyey Greenstein phase function, which allows realistic lighting effects for volumetric data. For specific applications the tool supports off axis stereo rendering, which makes it possible to create stereo pairs and 3D movies for immersive visualization.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>High usability was a design goal from the beginning. The MATLAB interface is built around a small set of classes that make it straightforward to configure scenes, adjust parameters, and generate animations programmatically. This makes the renderer suitable not only for research prototypes, but also for teaching and reproducible figure generation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After an initial active phase during my studies the project sat idle for several years. When I moved to Munich in 2021 I resumed work on the codebase, updated the toolchain, improved the documentation, and prepared the project for a proper open source release. The result was a journal publication in 2024 and a cleaned up public repository that others can build on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Volume Renderer for use with MATLAB is released under the GNU Affero General Public License version 3. The example scripts are licensed under MIT, so they can be easily reused and adapted. The full source code is available on GitHub, together with usage examples and build instructions.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links-and-resources">Links and Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Journal Publication (2024):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2673-6470/4/4/49">https://www.mdpi.com/2673-6470/4/4/49&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>GitHub Repository:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/raphiniert-com/volume_renderer">https://github.com/raphiniert-com/volume_renderer&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>OctoMap Contribution</title><link>/project/octomap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/octomap/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="efficient-octree-traversal-for-robot-navigation-with-octomap">Efficient octree traversal for robot navigation with OctoMap&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My first larger C++ project began in 2010 when I wrote my bachelor thesis in the context of OctoMap, the well known open source framework for probabilistic 3D mapping. The project marked my first real contact with C++ and introduced me to volumetric data structures, robotics concepts, and efficient tree based algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of the thesis was to investigate and accelerate octree traversal methods for ray based operations in 3D volumetric maps. Autonomous robots rely on probabilistic 3D models for collision free navigation and path planning, and OctoMap provides such models by storing occupancy information in a compressed octree structure. Insertions and updates are driven by raycasting and raytracing, which in turn depend heavily on traversal performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The work explored multiple traversal strategies within OctoMap and evaluated how shortcuts, reorganized traversal orderings, and memory handling affect the speed of ray based operations. The experiments demonstrated that raytracing can be accelerated through specific traversal shortcuts, while raycasting benefits significantly from improved memory management strategies. These optimizations showed measurable gains in the insertion and update cycle of 3D sensor data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Building on these findings, the thesis also introduced an approach for segmenting OctoMaps into connected components of free or occupied space. Two segmentation variants were implemented and analyzed, one optimized for the compressed octree representation, and one for the expanded representation. The resulting algorithms were statistically evaluated and demonstrated how connected components could form a foundation for later object recognition or higher level map analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was my entry point into robotics oriented software engineering and 3D data structures, and it remains a meaningful milestone from the early days of my academic path.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links-and-resources">Links and Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>OctoMap Project Homepage:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://octomap.github.io/">https://octomap.github.io/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>