<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Clinical Registries on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</title><link>/tags/clinical-registries/</link><description>Recent content in Clinical Registries on Raphael Schmitt — AI Researcher | Language Models, NLP &amp; Information Retrieval</description><generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/clinical-registries/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ESID Registry</title><link>/project/esid/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/esid/</guid><description>&lt;p>ESID was one of the most formative long-term projects in my early medical informatics career. Through the ESID Registry I had the opportunity to work at the intersection of clinical data quality, registry design, modern database engineering, and distributed reporting systems. It was also the first project where I was able to present work at international conferences early on, and where I could demonstrate empirically that plausibility checks directly lead to higher data quality — an insight that later influenced several follow-up systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the early phase of the redesigned ESID registry, the system itself had already been implemented by the core development group. My role focused on publishing the new registry through an Application Note and presenting its concepts and early insights at ESID meetings. In addition, I developed several of the technical components that became central to the operational ecosystem around the registry, most notably the reporting tool, various export mechanisms (including automated email-based exports), and supporting infrastructure for data access and data delivery. Through these contributions I helped make the registry more accessible, more analyzable, and more useful for both clinicians and researchers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A major part of my ESID work centered on the reporting and export infrastructure surrounding the registry. While the registry itself was already in place, its operational ecosystem required modernisation. I developed the reporting tool, which unified several existing data flows, including the integration of UKPID registry exports via custom software. As part of this effort, the underlying database was periodically migrated from MySQL to PostgreSQL in an automated pipeline, enabling more robust data handling and laying the foundation for secure, structured access mechanisms such as Row-Level Security. This environment later supported API-based data retrieval, export interfaces, and interactive reporting functions for both internal and external stakeholders. The pipeline was later stabilized and re-implemented as Snakemake workflow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With PostgreSQL in place, we implemented a modern API using the SubZero stack, enabling safe and structured data access. Row-Level Security (RLS) policies were deployed across all tables to guarantee user-specific and registry-specific permissions. In the internal area of the platform, permitted users could generate exports, including specialized outputs such as the APDS study dataset. The system was built around RabbitMQ and Socket-based notifications. The frontend was developed in React and consumed a GraphQL interface built on top of the API layer. The public-facing side provided global registry statistics, while the internal dashboard showed the subset of data relevant to the logged-in user’s registry assignment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later, there were plans to migrate the entire reporting solution to Apache Superset. Initial groundwork was completed: a connection to the user directory was implemented, and the database was preconfigured with RLS so that dashboards would automatically respect each user’s data access permissions. However, due to limited resources and the end of the contract period, the full migration was ultimately not carried out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The APDS study was an important use case within the ESID ecosystem. Its dataset required a human-readable export format despite being based on nested data structures. To make these structures visually intuitive, we created a color-coded Excel representation that allowed clinicians to interpret hierarchical data at a glance within a so called sparse spreadsheet. The tool was named Json2Xlsx and was later published in Software Impacts. This export mechanism supported numerous APDS publications and was also used for data exports to industry partners.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A further component connected to the ESID ecosystem involved the integration of ESID within the German PID-NET infrastructure using the OSSE registry framework. This was documented in a dedicated publication describing how the OSSE bridgehead enables interoperability between the customized ESID registry and the wider network of rare disease registries. While my own work focused primarily on reporting, export mechanisms, API access, and data delivery around ESID, this paper provides the architectural context in which our technical ecosystem operated: it shows how the ESID registry can participate in decentralized, federated queries without relinquishing data sovereignty, and how OSSE acts as an interoperability layer for national and international collaborative research. The approach demonstrated how a highly customized registry like ESID can connect to the OSSE platform via a free and maintainable toolchain, illustrating the broader interoperability landscape in which my ESID-related technical contributions were embedded.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, ESID represents a central pillar of my early work in registry design, data quality, API-driven architectures, and secure access control via PostgreSQL and RLS. It is one of the projects where methodological development, practical clinical utility, and research contributions came together in a meaningful way, and one that influenced how I approached subsequent registry and data pipeline projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links--resources">Links &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>New ESID Registry – Application Note:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/35/24/5367/5526873">https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/35/24/5367/5526873&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>ESID Reporting Tool:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://cci-reporting.uniklinik-freiburg.de/#/">https://cci-reporting.uniklinik-freiburg.de/#/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>ESID Registry Overview (2020, Frontiers in Immunology):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7578818/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7578818/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>ESID Registry Working Party:&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://esid.org/working-parties/registry-working-party/">https://esid.org/working-parties/registry-working-party/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>AL-PID Registry</title><link>/project/al-pid/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/project/al-pid/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="al-pid--from-a-legacy-access-structure-to-a-functional-clinical-registry">AL-PID – From a Legacy Access Structure to a Functional Clinical Registry&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>AL-PID was the very first project I worked on when I joined the CCI in 2015. What existed initially was a raw Microsoft Access database intended to serve as a registry for patients with ALPS and related primary immunodeficiencies. What was missing was everything required for actual clinical use: a user interface, a coherent data model, plausibility logic, and an export workflow suitable for downstream scientific analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal was therefore clear: transform a static legacy database into a usable, validated clinical registry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I developed a complete user interface in Microsoft Access and Visual Basic, inspired by ESID but built independently. Central to the system was a tree-structured plausibility logic implemented through event-driven hooks such as OnClick and OnChange. This logic ensured consistent, clinically meaningful data entry and protected the dataset from contradictory or incomplete inputs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A distinctive aspect of AL-PID was its dynamic, visually guided plausibility system. The UI did not simply validate data in the background, but actively controlled the user’s workflow by showing or hiding interface elements based on clinical context. Only when certain variables were selected did additional fields, sections, or action buttons appear. This approach allowed clinicians to focus on the exact data relevant to the case at hand, reduced cognitive load, and prevented invalid combinations from ever being entered. It was a lightweight but highly effective form of context-aware data entry entirely implemented within Access and VBA.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over time, AL-PID evolved not only at the UI level but also structurally. The original data model had grown organically and lacked clear boundaries between clinical entities. I refactored and abstracted the schema: redundant fields were consolidated, variable groups reorganized, and a clean separation between MDAT and IDAT was introduced to satisfy data protection requirements. The result was a modular and extensible data model that improved maintainability, validation, and long-term data quality. This evolving structure became the backbone that enabled stable exports for subsequent statistical workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During my later guest scientist period at the CCI, clinicians required a publication-ready export. We designed an Excel-based format that medical staff could populate without technical hurdles. I then implemented a Python-based exporter that converted the sheets into a standardized dataset suitable for further analysis. This workflow ultimately enabled a successful publication in The Lancet Haematology, marking both the scientific impact of the project and the maturity of the registry system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking back, AL-PID was a defining early project for me: a demanding but formative introduction to clinical registries, data modeling, and the practical realities of medical informatics. Many of the principles developed here later influenced my subsequent registry and data pipeline work, including ESID and OSSE-based systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="links--resources">Links &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Project Overview (CCI Freiburg):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.uniklinik-freiburg.de/cci/studien/alpsal-pid.html">https://www.uniklinik-freiburg.de/cci/studien/alpsal-pid.html&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>🤗 &lt;strong>Publication (The Lancet Haematology):&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanhae/article/PIIS2352-3026(23)00362-9">https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanhae/article/PIIS2352-3026(23)00362-9&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>